[
{
    "question": "The 2017 Ford GT features a structure in its bodywork referred to as a 'flying buttress' in architecture. On the vehicle, it appears as a tunnel, formed by a bridge over a dip in the bodywork. If the mass flow rate through the flying buttress is 3.592 kg/s when the car is moving 80 kilometers per hour, the velocity of air at the smallest cross section of the tunnel is 1.5 times the entrance, and the density of air is 1.293 kg/m^3, determine the area of the smallest point of the flying buttress.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np

m_flow = 3.592  # Mass flow rate (kg/s)
v1 = 80  # Air velocity at tunnel entrance (km/h)
rv = 1.5  # Ratio of velocity at point 2 to point 1
rho = 1.293  # Density (kg/m^3)

# Convert v1 into m/s
v1 = (v1 * 1000) / 3600

# Apply the mass flow rate equation to find area 1 (m_flow = rho*A*v)
A1 = m_flow / (rho * v1)

# Apply principle of conservation of mass (rho*A1*v1 = rho*A2*v2)
A2 = (A1 * v1) / (v1 * rv)

print("Smallest cross-sectional area in the flying buttress:", A2, "m^2.")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code utilizes conservation of mass in control volumes, which states that the mass flow rate into the volume must be equal to out of the volume. This means that using any 2 points in an enclosed wind tunnel as an entrance and exit for a control volume, their mass flow rates will be equal. The formula m_flow = rho*A*v allows us to find the cross-sectional inlet area, which then lets us set up an equation from m_flow1 = m_flow2 to find A2. Alternatively, one can use the given information to calculate v2, then use the mass flow rate equation to find A2 acknowledging conservation of mass.",
        "references": [
            "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flying_buttress"
        ]
    }
}
{
    "question": "Water flows through a pipe that decreases in radius towards the end. Along a certain streamline in the water, the initial flow velocity is 3 meters per second, at a pressure of 1 bar. At the end of the pipe, flow reaches a pressure of 0.8 bar. What is the flow velocity along the streamline the end of the pipe? Assume water density to be 1000 kg/m^3.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np

v1 = 3  # Initial flow velocity (m/s)
P1 = 1 # Initial flow pressure (bar)
P2 = 0.8 # Final flow pressure (bar)
rho = 1000 # Water density (kg/m^3)

# Convert pressure into pascals
P1 = (P1 * 100000)
P2 = (P2 * 100000)

# Apply the Bernouli's equation to find the velocity along the streamline at the end of the pipe (P1+((1/2)*rho*(v1^2)) = P2+((1/2)*rho*(v2^2)))
v2 = (((P1+(1/2)*rho*(v1**2)-P2)*2)/rho)**(1/2)

print("Flow velocity at the end of the pipe:", v2, "m/s.")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code utilizes Bernoulli's equation to find the flow velocity along a streamline. The pipe decreasing in radius can both throw people off by suggesting use of an equation involving cross-sectional area, or serve as a hint that flow properties will change. The phrase 'along a streamline' suggests that Bernoulli's equation should be used, because along a streamline, the result of bernoulli's equation stays constant regardless of changes in flow velocity or pressure."
    }
}
{
    "question": "Due to mineral buildup in a house's water pipes, there has been a 250 Pa drop in water pressure to the taps. If the bulk velocity of the water flow is 5 m/s, the pipe is 5 centimeters wide, and the total distance of pipe from the water resevoir to the sink is 200 meters, determine the friction generated by the mineral buildup in the pipes. Assume friction is 100% caused by mineral buildup, and that without it the pipes would have been frictionless. Also assume a straight pipe.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np

dP = 250  # Drop in water pressure (Pa)
L = 200 # Pipe length (m)
D = 5 # Pipe diameter (cm)
V = 5 # Bulk velocity (m/s)

# Convert pipe diameter into meters
D = D*0.01

# Apply the Hagen-Poiseuille equation to find the friction in the pipe (dP = (8*mu*V*L)/(R^2)) where mu is the friction
mu = (dP * (D/2)**2)/(8*V*L) 

print("Friction in pipe caused by mineral buildup:", mu, "N")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code applies the Hagen-Poisseuille equation, which states that the pressure losses in a pipe with friction is proportional to the flow velocity, pipe length, friction force, and pipe radius. It rearranges this relationship using the given information in the question to find the force of friction in the pipe."
    }
}
{
    "question": "0.5 kg of air in a piston is brought isobarically from 5 celcius to 10 celcius isobarically in a piston. If the c_p = 1010 J/(kg*k) and R = 287 J/(kg*k) for air, find the change in internal engergy, dU, of the air in the piston.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np

cp = 1010 # Isobaric specific heat capacity of air (J/(kg*K))
R = 287 # Specific gas constant of air (J/(kg*K))
T1 = 5 # Initial temperature of air in piston (C)
T2 = 10 # Final temperature of air in piston (C)
m = 0.5 # Mass of air in piston (kg)

# Find dh, the change in specific enthalpy (dh = cp * dT)
dh = cp * (T2-T1)

# Find Q, the heat introduced, acknowledging the process is isobaric (Q = m*dh)
Q = m * dh

# Find W utilizing ideal gas relations (W = p*dV, dV = (m*R*(T2-T1))/p)
W = m * R * (T2-T1)

# Calculate the change in internal energy (dU = Q-W)
dU = Q-W

print("Change in internal energy:", dU, "J")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code utilizes isobaric (constant pressure) equations for Q (Q=m*dH) and W (W=p*dV), as well as the ideal gas relation (pV=mRT). Most importantly, it relates the equation for work to the ideal gas relation to find the work throughout the process without knowing the pressure. This allows us to find the change in internal energy (U=Q-W)."
    }
}
{
    "question": "A prototype railgun uses pressure to fire a projectile. Within the barrel are two chambers, one with high air pressure and a volume of 1 liter and one evacuated. When a burst disc between the chambers is burst, the air in the high-pressure chamber is rapidly pulled to the evacuated chamber, which propels the projectile. If the volume of the high-pressure chamber contains 0.5 kg of air, the two chambers rapidly come to equilibrium, and there is a 231 J/K change in entropy, determine the volume of the evacuated chamber.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np
import math
e = math.e

V1 = 1 # Volume of high-pressure chamber (J/(kg*K))
R = 287 # Specific gas constant of air (J/(kg*K))
dS = 231 # Change in entropy (J/K)
m = 0.5 # Mass of air in chamber (kg)

# Given adiabatic process with no work, dU = m*cv*dT=0, meaning dT=0, resulting in
T2=T1

# Find ratio of total volume to V1 (V_rat=(Vtot/v1)=e^(dS/(m*R))
V_rat = e ** (dS/(m*R))

#Find volume of evacuated chamber (V2 = V_tot-V1)
V2 = (V_rat*V1) - V1


print("Volume of the evacuated chamber:", V2, "L")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the formula for the change in entropy to find the volume of a chamber in a system. The bursting of a barrier to join the chambers results in no work being done, while the process occuring rapidly results in no heat transfer. This results in no temperature change, making the entropy formula completely based on volume.",
        "references": [
            "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s2yIMJ4iayg"
        ]
    }
}
{
    "question": "A plane is flying through the air at mach 1.5. Using the moving plane as a reference point, If the temperature of the environment is 290 K, and the air at some point in front of the bow wave is slowed to 300 m/s, determine the temperature of the air at the same point.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np

T1 = 290 # Environmental temperature (K)
gamma = 1.4 # Specific heat capacity ratio (cp/cv) of air
v2 = 300 # Velocity at point 2 (m/s)
M1 = 1.5 # Mach number of environmental air

# Calculate the stagnation temperature of the enviroment (T01/T1 = 1+((gamma-1)/2)*M1^2)
T01 = (1+((gamma-1)/2)*(M1**2))*T1

# Calculate the temperature where airspeed is V2 (T01=T1+((v1^2)/2cp)=T2+((v2^2)/(2*cp))
T2 = T01-((v2**2)/(2*cp))


print("Temperature at second point: ", T2, "K")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code utilizes two different formulas for stagnation temperature, one using mach number and the other using temperature and velocity. The temperature and velocity equation with different conditions can be related using T01 = T1+((v1^2)/2cp) = T2+((v2^2)/(2*cp)."
    }
}
{
    "question": "A plane flies through the air with a mach number of 2. Air is deflected off of the 10 degree cockpit at an angle of 39.31 degrees. If the pressure of the air is 0.5 Bar at the plane's altitude, calculate the air pressure and mach number downstream of the shock.",
    "answer": {
        "code": """
import numpy as np
import math

M1 = 2 # Mach number of air relative to plane
theta = 10 # Angle of cockpit relative to direction of airflow (Degrees)
beta = 39.31 # Oblique shock angle relative to airflow (Degrees)
p1 = 0.5 # Air pressure at plane's altitude (bar)
gamma = 1.4 # Ratio of specific heat capacities

# Calculate the normal mach number relative to shock (Mn1 = M*sin(beta))
beta_radians = math.radians(beta)
Mn1 = M1 * math.sin(beta_radians)

# Calculate pressure downstream of shock ((1+((2*gamma)/(gamma+1))*(Mn1^2-1)*p1)
p2 = ((1+((2*gamma)/(gamma+1))*((Mn1**2)-1)*p1)

# Calculate downstream Mach number (M2 = Mn2/(sin(beta-theta)))
angle_radians = math.radians(beta-theta)
M2 = (((1+((gamma-1)/2)*(Mn1**2))/(gamma*(Mn1**2)-((gamma-1)/2)))**(1/2))/(math.sin(angle_radians))

print("Pressure downstream of shock: ", p2, "Bar. Mach number downstream of shock: ", M2, ".")
        """,
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the oblique shock relations to find the pressure and mach number downstream of the shock, utilizing the formulas listed in the notes above the corresponding lines of code.",
        "references": [
            "https://www.aerodynamics4students.com/gas-dynamics-and-supersonic-flow/table8.php"
        ]
    }
}
{
    "question": "Imagine a jet ejecting mass onto some flat surface. When calculating force acting on the surface by the jet, why can mass flow out of the control volume be ignored?",
    "answer": "Assuming the fluid is frictionless, the force on the surface by the jet is completely perpendicular to the surface. Because the surface acts as a wall that mass can't go past, all mass flow out of the control volume has a velocity parallel to the surface, with no element normal to the surface. As a result, the equation F = ((mfr)*(v))_out-((mfr)*(v))_in has a value v_out of 0, which makes the mass flow rate (mfr) out of the volume negligible."
}
{
    "question": "A pipe carries water from a lake to a power generator inside a dam. If the pipe diameter decreases along its length, how would the velocity and pressure be affected downstream?",
    "answer": "According to the mass flow rate equation m_flow = rho*A*v, as the diameter decreased, pipe area would decrease, thus according to conservation of mass the water velocity must increase. However, according to Bernoulli's equation (disregarding gravity), p + (1/2)*rho*(v^2) stays constant along a streamline. As a result, due to the increase in velocity, pressure would fall."
}
{
    "question": "A large boat moves out of a ferry port with solid, stationary walls. As the boat continues moving, what can one say about the velocity of water between the hull of the ship and the wall of the port? There are no waves or external sources of water flow disruption in the port.",
    "answer": "The velocity of water increases linearly the closer it is to the ship, until it approximately matches the ship's speed when in direct contact. This is a display of couette flow and shows the existence of varying levels of shear stresses in the water between the wall and the boat's hull."
}
{
    "question": "What are 4 assumptions that can be made of the fully restrained slow heating of an ideal gas by an external source to a higher temperature?",
    "answer": "1. Process is isochoric and thus has no work. 2. The process is quasi-equilibrium as it is heated slowly, allowing the temperature to evenly change throughout. 3. All change in internal energy must stem from heat transfer. 4. Gas pressure increases according to the ideal gas law pV = mRT."
}
{
    "question": "A gas is slowly cooled down in a piston that keeps the gas at a constant pressure. The piston is well-insulated. What is the change in entropy throughout this process?",
    "answer": "Because the piston is well-insulated, this is an adiabatic process. Furthermore, because the process is quasi-equilibrium and maintains constant pressure via piston, it is reversible. These two conditions mean that the process is isentropic, so the change in entropy is zero."
}
{
    "question": "How does a refrigerator follow the clausius statement of thermodynamics?",
    "answer": "The clausius statement states that one can't transfer heat from a colder reservoir to a hotter reservoir. Conceptually, a refrigerator uses a refrigerant to absorb heat from the inside of the fridge, which is the colder reservoir. This heat as well as some external work input is used to produce work via compression, and the excess heat from this process is expelled to the environment. This is how the refrigerator is able to transfer heat from a cold to a hot reservoir."
}
{
    "question": "A wind tunnel with a converging and diverging section is choked at the throat. It is applied in a situation where the pressure in the converging section decreases. What can be said of the goal of its application, in relation to it's Mach number?",
    "answer": "Given a decrease in pressure at the converging section, one can infer that the Mach number at the inlet is less subsonic. As a result, the goal of its application is presumably to increase the wind speed to sonic or supersonic speeds, where the Mach number is more than 1."
}
{
    "question": "What is the reason, function, and drawback for the section of a supersonic wind tunnel that comes after the non-choked diffuser?",
    "answer": "At the exit of a supersonic wind tunnel, the air pressure has significantly decreased due to shocks. Because of this, a compressor is necessary to bring this air back to the pressure required at the inlet, to maintain constant and consistent flow conditions in the wind tunnel. However, this compression causes an increase in heat of the air."
}
{
    "question": "How does the roughness of walls impact the effectiveness of airflow in underground tunnels, and how might this be a problem? (Hint: what compressible fluid mechanics concept involves a long tunnel with friction?)",
    "answer": "A rough underground tunnel is a real-life example of fanno-flow. The roughness of the walls increases friction on airflow, which results in slowed airflow closer to the wall. Furthermore, in most practical non-experimentation situations, wind entering the tunnel would be subsonic. In fanno-flow, the slowed airflow near the wall causes the air near the center of the tunnel to progressively increase in speed and decrease in pressure until it is choked. These high wind speeds and low air pressure are the problem, especially if in a tunnel with human workers."
}
]